Our emotions influence every aspect of our lives,
عواطفنا تؤثر على كل نواحي حياتنا،
from our health and how we learn, to how we do business and make decisions,
من صحتنا وطريقة تعلمنا إلى كيفية تأدية أعمالنا واتخاذنا للقرارات
big ones and small.
الصغيرة منها أو الكبيرة.
Our emotions also influence how we connect with one another.
كما أنها تؤثر في كيفية تواصلنا مع بعضنا.
We've evolved to live in a world like this,
فقد تطورنا لنعيش في عالم كهذا،
but instead, we're living more and more of our lives like this --
ولكننا نعيش حياتنا أكثر فأكثر بهذا الشكل --
this is the text message from my daughter last night --
هذه رسالة نصية أرسلتها لي ابنتي الليلة الماضية --
in a world that's devoid of emotion.
في عالم منزوع المشاعر.
So I'm on a mission to change that.
أنا في مهمة لتغيير ذلك.
I want to bring emotions back into our digital experiences.
أود إعادة المشاعر إلى تجاربنا الرقمية.
I started on this path 15 years ago.
انطلقت على هذا الدرب منذ 15 سنة.
I was a computer scientist in Egypt,
كنت عالمة حاسوب في مصر،
and I had just gotten accepted to a Ph.D. program at Cambridge University.
وكنت قد قُبِلت للتو في برنامج للدكتوراه بجامعة كامبريدج.
So I did something quite unusual
وقمت وقتها بشيء غير اعتيادي
for a young newlywed Muslim Egyptian wife:
بالنسبة لفتاة مصرية مسلمة ومتزوجة حديثاً:
With the support of my husband, who had to stay in Egypt,
بدعم من زوجي الذي ظل في مصر،
I packed my bags and I moved to England.
حزمت حقائبي وانتقلت إلى انجلترا.
At Cambridge, thousands of miles away from home,
وفي كامبريدج بعيدا عن منزلي بآلاف الأميال،
I realized I was spending more hours with my laptop
أدركت أني أقضي وقتا أكبر أمام حاسوبي
than I did with any other human.
مما كنت أفعل مع الناس.
Yet despite this intimacy, my laptop had absolutely no idea how I was feeling.
ورغم كل تلك الألفة بيننا لم يكن لدى حاسوبي أية فكرة عما أشعر به.
It had no idea if I was happy,
لم تكن لديه أية فكرة إن كنت فرحة
having a bad day, or stressed, confused,
أو إن كان نهاري سيئاً أو أنني مرهقة، قلقة،
and so that got frustrating.
وقد أصبح الأمر محبطاً.
Even worse, as I communicated online with my family back home,
بل أن الأمر ساء عندما كنت أتصل بأسرتي،
I felt that all my emotions disappeared in cyberspace.
بحيث بدأت أحس بمشاعري تختفي في الفضاء الإلكتروني.
I was homesick, I was lonely, and on some days I was actually crying,
كنت أحن للوطن وكنت وحيدة بل إني كنت أبكي في بعض الأيام،
but all I had to communicate these emotions was this.
لكن الوسيلة التي كنت أنقل بها مشاعري،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Today's technology has lots of I.Q., but no E.Q.;
قد تملك التقنية اليوم نسبة ذكاء كبيرة لكنها تفتقد للمشاعر؛
lots of cognitive intelligence, but no emotional intelligence.
الكثير من الذكاء الإدراكي لكن دون ذكاء عاطفي.
So that got me thinking,
وهذا جعلني أفكر،
what if our technology could sense our emotions?
ماذا لو كان بإمكان تقنيتنا إدراك مشاعرنا؟
What if our devices could sense how we felt and reacted accordingly,
ماذا لو كان بإمكان أجهزتنا أن تحس بمشاعرنا وتتفاعل معنا على أساسها،
just the way an emotionally intelligent friend would?
كما كان ليفعل معكم صديق؟
Those questions led me and my team
وقد قادتني هذه الأسئلة وفريقي
to create technologies that can read and respond to our emotions,
إلى ابتكار تقنية قادرة على قراءة مشاعرنا والتفاعل معها،
and our starting point was the human face.
وكانت نقطة انطلاقنا من الوجه.
So our human face happens to be one of the most powerful channels
يعتبر وجهنا أقوى الوسائل
that we all use to communicate social and emotional states,
التي نستخدمها جميعا في التعبير عن حالاتنا الاجتماعية والعاطفية،
everything from enjoyment, surprise,
عن كل شيء عن الفرح والتفاجئ
empathy and curiosity.
والتعاطف والفضول.
In emotion science, we call each facial muscle movement an action unit.
نسمي في علم المشاعر كل حركة لعضلة الوجه بالحركة كوحدة قياس.
So for example, action unit 12,
فمثلا الحركة 12،
it's not a Hollywood blockbuster,
ليست بفيلم هوليوودي ضخم،
it is actually a lip corner pull, which is the main component of a smile.
في الواقع هي شد الشفتين لرسم البسمة.
Try it everybody. Let's get some smiles going on.
جربوها جميعا. دعونا نرسم بعض البسمات.
Another example is action unit 4. It's the brow furrow.
المثال الثاني هو الحركة 4. تقطيب الجبين.
It's when you draw your eyebrows together
وهذا عندما تقاربون بين حواجبكم
and you create all these textures and wrinkles.
لتظهر تلك الأخاديد والخطوط على جباهكم.
We don't like them, but it's a strong indicator of a negative emotion.
نحن لا نحبها لكنها علامة قوية على مشاعر سلبية.
So we have about 45 of these action units,
لدينا حوالي 45 حركة كوحدات قياس،
and they combine to express hundreds of emotions.
نجمع بينها للتعبير على المئات من المشاعر.
Teaching a computer to read these facial emotions is hard,
من الصعب تعليم الحاسوب كيفية قراءتها،
because these action units, they can be fast, they're subtle,
لأننا نقوم بتلك الحركات في رمشة عين، إنها خفية،
and they combine in many different ways.
ويمكن الجمع بينها بطرق مختلفة ومتعددة.
So take, for example, the smile and the smirk.
وخذ على سبيل المثال، البسمة العادية والصفراء.
They look somewhat similar, but they mean very different things.
قد تبدوان متشابهتين لكنهما بمعنيين جد مختلفين.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So the smile is positive,
فالبسمة العادية إيجابية المعنى
a smirk is often negative.
والصفراء في الغالب سلبيه.
Sometimes a smirk can make you become famous.
وقد تجعلكم البسمة الصفراء أحيانا مشهورين.
But seriously, it's important for a computer to be able
لكن وبشكل جدي، من المهم أن يكون الحاسوب قادراً
to tell the difference between the two expressions.
على التفريق بين هذين التعبيرين.
So how do we do that?
فكيف نفعل ذلك؟
We give our algorithms
أضفنا لخوارزمياتنا
tens of thousands of examples of people we know to be smiling,
العشرات من الآلاف من الأمثلة لأشخاص نعلم أنهم يبتسمون بحق،
from different ethnicities, ages, genders,
من مختلف الأعراق والأعمار والأجناس،
and we do the same for smirks.
ونفس الشيء للبسمة الصفراء.
And then, using deep learning,
وبعدها باستخدام عملية معقدة
the algorithm looks for all these textures and wrinkles
تبحث الخوارزمية على جميع تلك الأخاديد والخطوط
and shape changes on our face,
وعلى الاختلافات الصغيرة على وجوهنا،
and basically learns that all smiles have common characteristics,
التوصل إلى أن جميع البسمات العادية لديها مميزات مشتركة،
all smirks have subtly different characteristics.
وأن البسمات الصفراء لديها مميزات مختلفة خفية.
And the next time it sees a new face,
وفي المرة القادمة عند رؤيتها لوجه جديد
it essentially learns that
تتعرف الخوارزمية في الأساس
this face has the same characteristics of a smile,
بأن هذا الوجه لديه نفس مميزات البسمة العادية،
and it says, "Aha, I recognize this. This is a smile expression."
فتقول: "أنا أعرف هذه البسمة."
So the best way to demonstrate how this technology works
وأفضل طريقة لتوضيح كيفية عمل هذه التقنية
is to try a live demo,
هي تجربة عرض مباشر.
so I need a volunteer, preferably somebody with a face.
أنا بحاجة لمتطوع، ومن الأفضل أن يمتلك وجهاً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Cloe's going to be our volunteer today.
كلوي هي متطوعتنا اليوم.
So over the past five years, we've moved from being a research project at MIT
خلال السنوات 5 الماضية، انتقلنا من مرحلة مشروع بحث بمعهد ماساتشوستس للتقنية
to a company,
إلى شركة،
where my team has worked really hard to make this technology work,
حيث عمل فريقي بجد لجعل هذه التقنية تعمل،
as we like to say, in the wild.
كما يقال، في الطبيعة.
And we've also shrunk it so that the core emotion engine
كما قمنا بتصغيرحجمها
works on any mobile device with a camera, like this iPad.
لتعمل مع كافة الهواتف النقالة ذات الكاميرا كهذا الآي باد.
So let's give this a try.
دعونا إذا نجربها.
As you can see, the algorithm has essentially found Cloe's face,
كما تلاحظون، حددت الخوارزمية تقاسيم وجه كلوي
so it's this white bounding box,
في هذا الإطار الأبيض
and it's tracking the main feature points on her face,
وهي تبحث على النقط الرئيسية في وجهها،
so her eyebrows, her eyes, her mouth and her nose.
وهي حاجبيها وعينيها وفمها وأنفها.
The question is, can it recognize her expression?
والسؤال هو، هل ستتمكن من التعرف على تعابير وجهها؟
So we're going to test the machine.
سنختبر الآن الآلة لنعرف.
So first of all, give me your poker face. Yep, awesome. (Laughter)
في البداية، أود رؤية وجه لاعب الورق. نعم، رائع. (ضحك)
And then as she smiles, this is a genuine smile, it's great.
وبينما هي تبتسم، هذه ابتسامة جميلة، رائع.
So you can see the green bar go up as she smiles.
يمكنكم ملاحظة الشريط الأخضر يرتفع كلما ابتسمت.
Now that was a big smile.
كانت هذه ابتسامة مشرقة.
Can you try a subtle smile to see if the computer can recognize?
هل يمكنك الابتسام خفية لنرى إن كان الحاسوب سيتعرف عليها؟
It does recognize subtle smiles as well.
لقد تعرف على الابتسامة الخفية أيضا.
We've worked really hard to make that happen.
لقد عملنا بجد لتحقيق هذا.
And then eyebrow raised, indicator of surprise.
وبعدها رفع الحاجبين علامة المفاجأة.
Brow furrow, which is an indicator of confusion.
تقطيب الحاجبين علامة الارتباك.
Frown. Yes, perfect.
تقطيب. نعم، رائع.
So these are all the different action units. There's many more of them.
كانت هذه جميع الحركات المختلفة. وهناك العديد منها.
This is just a slimmed-down demo.
كان هذا عرضا بسيطا.
But we call each reading an emotion data point,
ونسمي كل نقطة تم التعرف عليها بنقطة بيانات عاطفية،
and then they can fire together to portray different emotions.
وبعد تمازجها معا تقدم لنا علامات عن مختلف المشاعر.
So on the right side of the demo -- look like you're happy.
وعلى يمين العرض -- يبدو أنك سعيدة.
So that's joy. Joy fires up.
هذا مؤشر الفرح ينطلق.
And then give me a disgust face.
والآن تعبير بالقرف.
Try to remember what it was like when Zayn left One Direction.
حاولي تذكر شعورك عندما ترك زين فرقة ون دايركشن.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah, wrinkle your nose. Awesome.
نعم، تقلص أنفك. رائع.
And the valence is actually quite negative, so you must have been a big fan.
انظروا إلى المقياس إنه جد سلبي، لابد وأنك معجبة كبيرة.
So valence is how positive or negative an experience is,
يبين هذا المقياس إن كانت التجربة إيجابية أو سلبية،
and engagement is how expressive she is as well.
و"الالتزام" مستوى التعبير.
So imagine if Cloe had access to this real-time emotion stream,
تخيلوا لو كان بإمكان كلوي الوصول إلى هذه البيانات العاطفية المباشرة،
and she could share it with anybody she wanted to.
ومشاركتها مع من تريد.
Thank you.
شكرا جزيلا كلوي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So, so far, we have amassed 12 billion of these emotion data points.
لقد جمعنا لغاية الآن 12 مليار نقطة بيانات عاطفية تلك.
It's the largest emotion database in the world.
وهي أكبر قاعدة بيانات عاطفية في العالم.
We've collected it from 2.9 million face videos,
وجمعناها من 2,9 مليون فيديو وجه،
people who have agreed to share their emotions with us,
لأشخاص وافقوا على مشاركة مشاعرهم معنا،
and from 75 countries around the world.
ومن 75 دولة حول العالم.
It's growing every day.
وهي تكبر كل يوم.
It blows my mind away
وقد أذهلني
that we can now quantify something as personal as our emotions,
كيف أنه أصبح بمقدورنا قياس شيء شخصي كمشاعرنا،
and we can do it at this scale.
وأن نفعل ذلك على هذا المستوى.
So what have we learned to date?
فما الذي تعلمناه إلى اليوم؟
Gender.
النوع.
Our data confirms something that you might suspect.
تؤكد بياناتنا أمر لربما تتوقعونه.
Women are more expressive than men.
النساء كن أكثر تعبيرا من الرجال.
Not only do they smile more, their smiles last longer,
ليس فقط أنهن الأكثر ابتساما بل لوقت أطول أيضاً
and we can now really quantify what it is that men and women
ويمكننا اليوم قياس ما يتفاعل معه الرجال والنساء
respond to differently.
بشكل مختلف.
Let's do culture: So in the United States,
من الجانب الثقافي: في الولايات المتحدة،
women are 40 percent more expressive than men,
من النساء هن 40% أكثر تعبيرا من الرجال،
but curiously, we don't see any difference in the U.K. between men and women.
لكن الغريب أنهما متساويان في المملكة المتحدة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Age: People who are 50 years and older
العمري: الأشخاص من 50 سنة فما فوق
are 25 percent more emotive than younger people.
هم 25% أكثر تعبيرا من الشباب.
Women in their 20s smile a lot more than men the same age,
النساء في سن 20 يبتسمن أكثر من الرجال في نفس السن،
perhaps a necessity for dating.
ربما لضرورة التعارف.
But perhaps what surprised us the most about this data
لكن ما فاجأنا أكثر في هذه البيانات
is that we happen to be expressive all the time,
هو أننا دائمي التعبير عن مشاعرنا،
even when we are sitting in front of our devices alone,
حتى عندما نكون جالسين أمام أجهزتنا لوحدنا،
and it's not just when we're watching cat videos on Facebook.
وليس فقط عندما نكون بصدد مشاهدة فيديوهات القطط على الفيسبوك.
We are expressive when we're emailing, texting, shopping online,
بل إننا نعبر أثناء كتابة رسالة أو التسوق على الإنترنت
or even doing our taxes.
أو حتى أثناء حسابنا للضريبة نهاية السنة.
Where is this data used today?
فيما تستخدم هذه البيانات حاليا؟
In understanding how we engage with media,
في فهم كيفية التعامل مع وسائل الإعلام
so understanding virality and voting behavior;
فهم الظواهر الشائعة وسلوكيات التصويت؛
and also empowering or emotion-enabling technology,
وكذلك تعزيز أو تمكين التقنية من المشاعر،
Emotion-enabled wearable glasses can help individuals
نظرات قارئة للمشاعر ستساعد ضعاف البصر
who are visually impaired read the faces of others,
في التعرف على تعابير وجوه الآخرين،
and it can help individuals on the autism spectrum interpret emotion,
ويمكن أن تساعد مرضى التوحد تأويل المشاعر،
something that they really struggle with.
وهو أمر يعانون منه كثيرا.
In education, imagine if your learning apps
في التعليم، تخيلوا إن كانت تطبيقاتكم التعليمية
sense that you're confused and slow down,
تحس بارتباككم فتبطئ الوتيرة
or that you're bored, so it's sped up,
أو بمللكم فتسرعها،
just like a great teacher would in a classroom.
كما قد يفعل أي مدرس متمرس في القسم.
What if your wristwatch tracked your mood,
تخيلوا ساعتكم تخبركم بمزاجكم
or your car sensed that you're tired,
أو أن تحس سيارتكم بأنكم تعبين
or perhaps your fridge knows that you're stressed,
أو أن تعرف ثلاجتكم بأنكم متوترين
so it auto-locks to prevent you from binge eating. (Laughter)
فتقفل تلقائيا لمنعكم من الأكل بشراهة. (ضحك)
What if, when I was in Cambridge,
ماذا لو تمكنت، عندما كنت في كامبريدج،
I had access to my real-time emotion stream,
من الوصول إلى بياناتي العاطفية المباشرة،
and I could share that with my family back home in a very natural way,
وتشاركتها مع أسرتي في الوطن بطريقة طبيعية،
just like I would've if we were all in the same room together?
كما كنت لأفعل لو كنا جميعا في الغرفة نفسها؟
I think five years down the line,
أعتقد أنه خلال السنوات الخمس القادمة،
all our devices are going to have an emotion chip,
ستحتوي جميع أجهزتنا على شريحة مشاعر
and we won't remember what it was like when we couldn't just frown at our device
وسننسى بعدها كيف أننا كنا نعبس
and our device would say, "Hmm, you didn't like that, did you?"
أمام أجهزتنا فلا ترد قائلة: "أنت لا تحب هذا، أليس كذلك؟"
Our biggest challenge is that there are so many applications of this technology,
التحدي الكبير الذي يواجهنا هو أن هناك طرق متعددة لاستعمال هذه التقنية،
my team and I realize that we can't build them all ourselves,
وقد أدركت وفريقي بأنه لا يمكننا ابتكارها جميعا بمفردنا،
so we've made this technology available so that other developers
لذا أتحنا هذه التقنية ليتمكن باقي المطورين
can get building and get creative.
من المساهمة في التطوير والابتكار.
We recognize that there are potential risks
ونحن نعترف بأن هناك مخاطر محتملة
and potential for abuse,
وإمكانية لاستغلالها،
but personally, having spent many years doing this,
لكن شخصيا، وبعد أن قضيت عدة سنوات في هذا العمل،
I believe that the benefits to humanity
أؤمن بأن الفوائد التي ستجنيها البشرية
from having emotionally intelligent technology
من الحصول على تقنية ذات ذكاء عاطفي
far outweigh the potential for misuse.
أكبر بكثير من احتمال سوء استخدامها.
And I invite you all to be part of the conversation.
وأدعوكم جميعا لتكونوا جزءا من النقاش.
The more people who know about this technology,
فكلما كان عدد الأشخاص المطلعين على هذه التقنية أكبر
the more we can all have a voice in how it's being used.
كلما كان لنا رأي في طريقة استخدامها.
So as more and more of our lives become digital,
وبينما تصبح حياتنا رقمية أكثر فأكثر،
we are fighting a losing battle trying to curb our usage of devices
فإننا نخوض معركة خاسرة بمحاولتنا للحد من استخدام الأجهزة
in order to reclaim our emotions.
من أجل المطالبة بمشاعرنا.
So what I'm trying to do instead is to bring emotions into our technology
وما أحاول القيام به هو تمكين أجهزتنا من المشاعر
and make our technologies more responsive.
وجعل تقنياتنا أكثر تفاعلا.
So I want those devices that have separated us
وأود من تلك الأجهزة التي فرقتنا
to bring us back together.
أن تكون سبباً في جمعنا معاً.
And by humanizing technology, we have this golden opportunity
وبتأنيس التقنية نكون أمام فرصة ذهبية
to reimagine how we connect with machines,
لمراجعتنا لطريقة تواصلنا مع الآلات،
and therefore, how we, as human beings,
وبالتالي، كيف يمكننا، كبشر،
connect with one another.
بأن نتواصلنا فيما بيننا
Thank you.
شكراً جزيلا.